Register of the Krzysztof Jagielski papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Krzysztof Jagielski papers
1969-2002
2000C50
Hoover Institution Archives
7 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder, 2 sound discs (5.4 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, clandestine literature, leaflets, serial issues, other printed matter, sound recordings, photographs, and memorabilia relating to activities of Solidarność in Poland, with a particular emphasis on Szczecin and the region Pomorze Zachodnie.
Jagielski, Krzysztof, 1936-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Krzysztof Jagielski was born June 28, 1936 in Poznan. From the late 1950s until the early 1980s, he worked, fulfilling various duties from assistant steward to financial steward with the Polska Żegluga Morska and the Polskie Linie Oceaniczne (PLO).
In August 1980, he helped found the strike committee of PLO workers in Szczecin, and he became its chairman. He also became part of the leadership of the Solidarity movement in Pomorze Zachodnie (Western Pomerania). He served as the chairman of the Komitet Strajkowy Polskich Linii Oceanicznych and as a member of the Prezydium Komisji Zakładowej PLO, Zarząd Regionu Pomorza Zachodniego, and Krajowa Komisja Zjazdowa. Jagielski was arrested as part of the crackdown on the Szczecin shipyards in December 1981 during the introduction of martial law in Poland, after which he was imprisoned in Bydgoszcz. In March 1982, the legal proceedings against him were discontinued.
On June 23, 1983, Jagielski immigrated to West Berlin, where he continued as a Solidarity activist with the Emigracyjny Klub „Solidarność.” In 1992, he published a monograph about Solidarność activities in Szczecin in the early 1980s, Za burtą legendy. While the collection he assembled is in many ways a reflection of his own political activities in the 1980s, it can be better understood as a record of the Solidarity movement in Szczecin from 1980 to 1982, as well as of the activities of Solidarity activists abroad in the mid-to-late 1980s.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Krzysztof Jagielski are composed of Jagielski's personal archive of the Solidarność movement both while living in Poland and as an émigré living in West Berlin. The collection contains newspaper clippings, clandestine literature, leaflets, photographs, graphics, sound recordings, and memorabilia relating both specifically to events in which he was personally involved and more generally to the movement, which he collected. Small parts of the collection were clearly acquired by Jagielski after the events which the materials describe as he was doing the research for his 1992 monograph on the topic.
The core components of the collection are in the Chronological File, which has two basic parts: 1) the materials produced by Jagielski and his Szczecin-based associates between August 1980 and December 1981 as the initial movement was unfolding and 2) materials produced by him and émigré associates in the mid and late 1980s as part of the Emigracyjny klub “Solidarność”. Jagielski's arrangement has been preserved. Therefore, strike leaflets, meeting notes, correspondence, conference materials, and memorabilia acquired by Jagielski; delegate election materials; clandestine literature; and drafts for the production of clandestine literature are all in this series. For the period August 1980 to December 1981, the arrangement is chronological, but approximate arrangements that Jagielski imposed and that have to do with the development or activity of a specific committee have been preserved where possible. The folder titles in the Chronological File, therefore, should not be understood as the only place to find documents relating to a specific committee or conference; rather, they indicate the majority of the documents that will be found in a particular folder. The organizing activity of a local Szczecin factory bleeds into inter-factory and regional organizing. For the émigré period covering the mid-to-late 1980s, this section of the Chronological File is largely correspondence, which was arranged numerically.
The Correspondence series, therefore, only contains correspondence which Jagielski separated and marked as private, but it is still largely about his political activity. He arranged the materials roughly chronologically but with exceptions to keep a communication history with one correspondent together, and this original arrangement has been preserved.
Documents relating to the Polish government crackdown in December 1981 and the ensuing legal process are arranged both in the Biographical File and Chronological File following Jagielski's own filing arrangement. The Biographical File contains original documents relating specifically to Jagielski and his wife, personally, as well as copies of declassified government records produced throughout the 1980s about him and other strike participants from the Sąd Pomorskiego Okręgu Wojskowego w Bydgoszczy. Jagielski obtained these copies in 2003 through an official records request. Original documents related to the December 13, 1981 strike itself and the Bydgoszcz process about the strike, from late 1981 and early 1982, are in the Chronological File.
The Printed Matter series contains Jagielski's own publications, Za burtą legendy being the most significant to this collection and in many ways a useful guide to its contents. The majority of the other publications in this series are related specifically to the Szczecin part of the Solidarity movement and form another useful key to investigating the contents of the Chronological File.
Addtionally, the Sound Recordings series contains numerous recordings from Solidarity-related events in 1980 and 1981 and the crackdown, as well as emigration activities as late as 1987.
Finally, smaller graphic materials and memorabilia items can be found throughout the Chronological File as Jagielski had arranged them, but the largest sections of materials not easily associated with a specific event or date are at the end of the Chronological File, with large items in the Oversize Material series.
NSZZ "Solidarność" (Labor organization); Poland--History--1980-1989.; Dissenters--Poland.; Audiotapes.
- Biographical File, 1969-1991
  - Jagielski, Krzysztof, c.v. and Krzysztof and Magdalena Jagielski legal documents, 1969-1983 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Kopie z Akt Sądowych POW, sygn. IPN By 51/38-43, t.I, 1981 December (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Kopie z Akt Sądowych POW, sygn. IPN By 51/38-43, t.II, 1981 December (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Kopie z Akt Sądowych POW, sygn. IPN By 51/38-43, t.III, 1982 January (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Kopie z Akt Sądowych POW, sygn. IPN By 51/38-43, t.IV, 1982 January-February (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Kopie z Akt Sądowych POW, sygn. IPN By 51/38-43, t.V, 1982 February-March (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Kopie z Akt Sądowych POW, sygn. IPN By 51/38-43, t.VI, 1982 March-April (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Akta Prokuratora, Sygn. IPN Po 93/69 (Kopie), 1984-1989 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Rewizja Nadzwyczajna, Sąd Najwższy, Izba Wojskowa w Warszawie, 1991 November-December (Box-folder 1: 9)
- Correspondence, 1982-1990
  - 1982 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - 1983-1984 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - 1985-1990 (Box-folder 1: 12)
- Chronological File, 1980-1983
  - Komitet Strajkowy Polskich Linii Oceanicznych, 1980 August 25-26 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Komitet Strajkowy Polskich Linii Oceanicznych, 1980 August 27 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Komitet Strajkowy Polskich Linii Oceanicznych, 1980 August 28-30 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Międzyzakładowy Komitet Strajkowy Szczecin, 1980 August (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Komisja Robotnicza Polskich Linii Oceanicznych, 1980 September (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Komisja Robotnicza Polskich Linii Oceanicznych (Drafts), 1980 September-October (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Photographs of Solidarity meetings and leaders, 1980 August-September (Box-folder 2: 7)
    Arrangement Statement
    Negatives for slides of Warszawa URSUS event, 1980 September 18, have been moved to Box 8.
  - Międzyzakładowa Komisja Robotnicza w Szczecinie, 1980 October-November (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - 1 zakładowe zebranie delegatów PLO (Gdynia 7.01.1981) and various, 1980 November-1981 February (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Memorabilia, Strike committee PLO and general Solidarność, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Memorabilia, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    Scope and Contents note
    Pins, coins, and stickers; some of the first in Poland produced in Szczecin.
  - Originały komunikatów "Bydgoszcz" KZ NSZZ "Solidarność" PLO w Szczecinie, 1981 March (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Originały komunikatów "Bydgoszcz" KZ NSZZ "Solidarność" PLO w Szczecinie (binder), 1981 March (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Międzyzakładowa Komisja Robotnicza w Szczecinie, Prezydium, 1981 March (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Wybory do Zarządu regionu "Pomorza Zachodniego", 1981 April-June (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - I walny zjazd delegatów Pomorza Zachodniego (NSZZ Solidarność), photographs and memorabilia, 1981 May-June (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Zarząd regionu Pomorza Zachodniego NSZZ "Solidarność", 1981 July-August (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - I krajowy zjazd delegatów NSZZ "Solidarność" Gdańsk, 1981 September (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - I krajowy zjazd delegatów NSZZ "Solidarność" Gdańsk, 1981 September-October (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - I krajowy zjazd delegatów NSZZ "Solidarność" Gdańsk, photographs and memorabilia, 1981 September-October (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Zarząd regionu Pomorza Zachodniego NSZZ "Solidarność" Gdańsk, 1981 October-November (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Strajk stocznia "Warski" Szczecin, 1981 December (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Proces Bydgoszcz, 1982 January-February (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Proces Bydgoszcz, 1982 March (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Memorabilia and miscellaneous, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Emigracyjny klub "Solidarność", 1985 July-December (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Emigracyjny klub "Solidarność", 1986 January-March (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Emigracyjny klub "Solidarność", 1986 April-August (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Emigracyjny klub "Solidarność", 1986 July-September (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Emigracyjny klub "Solidarność", 1986 October-1987 February (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Emigracyjny klub "Solidarność", 1987 March-1993 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Solidarność postage stamps and graphics, 1976-1992 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Memorabilia and miscellaneous, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Memorabilia and miscellaneous, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 5: 3)
- Printed Matter, 1980-2002
  - Monographs
    - Jagielski, Krzysztof. Za burtą legendy.. Szczecin: Punkt, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Jagielski, Krzysztof. Karczma "Pod Krzywym Ryjem" i inne opowiadania. Warszawa Agencja Wydawn. CB, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Jagielski, Krzysztof. „Szwecowa” in Słowo: kwartalnik. Berlin: Klub Inteligencji Katolickiej w Berlinie. Nr. 51, 2000 Fall (Box 5)
    - Jagielski, Krzysztof. „Ein Denkmal fur Józef Retinger = Pomnik dla Józefa Retingera” in Das Wort: Quartalschrift = Słowo. Berlin: Klub der Katholischen Intelligenz. Nr. 58, 2002 Fall (Box 5)
    - Babiński, Andrzej, Janusz Sokalski, Zdzisław Sośnicki. Szczeciński sierpień 1980. Szczecin: Naczelna Red. Wydawnictw Pozaprasowych (Box 5)
    - Bydgoski marzec ­ prowokacja nieukarana: farsa czy porozumienie warszawskie, kim są chłopcy z tamtych dni, jak długo potrwa antrakt? [Bydgoszcz]: MKZ NSZZ "Solidarność" Regionu Bydgoskiego, 1981 (Box 6)
    - NSZZ "Solidarność". Protokóły porozumień Gdańsk, Szczecin, Jastrzẹbie. Statut NSZZ "Solidarność". Warszawa: Krajowa Agencia Wydawnicza, 1980 (Box 6)
    - NSZZ "Solidarność" Region Pomorza Zachodniego. Protokóły porozumień Gdańsk, Szczecin, Jastrzẹbie. Statut NSZZ "Solidarność". Warszawa: Krajowa Agencia Wydawnicza, (Teki Historyczne; 1/1981), 1980 (Box 6)
    - Szejnert, Małgorzata, Tomasz Zalewski. Szczecin: grudzień ­ sierpień ­ grudzień. Warszawa: Niezależna Oficyna Wydawnicza, 1984 (Box 6)
  - Serials
    - Jedność. [Szczecin]: Zarząd regionu NSZZ „Solidarność” Pomorza Zachodniego, 1982 July 23 - 1988 January (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Komunikat. Szczecin: Międzyzakładowa Komisja Robotnicza, 1980 October 22 - 1981 January 7 (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - Komunikat. Szczecin: Międzyzakładowa Komisja Robotnicza, 1981 January 8-April 24 (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - Komunikat: Prezydium Zarządu Regionu Pomorza Zachodniego. NSZZ Solidarność. Szczecin: [Zarząd regionu NSZZ „Solidarność” Pomorza Zachodniego], 1981 August 19-December 10 (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - Samorząd: biuletyn informacyjny. Gdynia, Gdansk, Szczecin: Grupa inicjatywna d/s Samorządu w Polskich Liniach Oceanicznych, 1981 October 12 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - Solidarność Uniwersytecka. Katowice: NSZZ Solidarność, 1981 November 6 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - Solidarność Wielkopolski: Pismo NSZZ Solidarność MKZ­Wielkopolski. Poznań: MKZ NSZZ Solidarność Wielkopolska, 1981 June 28 (Box-folder 6: 7)
    - Wolny związkowiec: organ Niezależnych Samorządnych Związków Zawodowych Huta "Katowice". Dąbrowa Górnicza: NSZZ "Solidarność" Huta "Katowice,", 1981 April 3-July 3 (Box-folder 6: 8)
    - Miscellaneous Solidarity-related news clippings and publications, 1980-1984 (Box-folder 6: 9)
    - Jedność: organ Międzyzakładowego Komitetu Strajkowego przy Stoczni im. A. Warskiego. Szczecin: Międzyzakładowy Komitet Strajkowy, 1980 August 24 - 1981 December 11 (Box 7)
    - Tygodnik Solidarność. Warszawa: Krajowa Komisja Porozumiewawcza NSZZ "Solidarność", 1981 April 3-December 11 (Box 7)
- Sound Recordings, 1980-1989
  - Solidarność, Sierpień, Szczecin, 1980 August 27 (Box 8)
    1 compact sound cassette
  - Solidarność, Sierpień, Szczecin, 1980 August 28 (Box 8)
  - Solidarność, Sierpień, Szczecin, 1980 August 29 (Box 8)
  - Solidarność, Sierpień, Szczecin, 1980 August 30 (Box 8)
  - KKR, 1980 September 22 (Box 8)
    2 compact sound cassettes
  - KKR, 1980 October 6 (Box 8)
    4 compact sound cassettes
  - KKR, 1980 October 13 (Box 8)
  - KKR, 1980 October 31 (Box 8)
  - Rok 1980, miscellaneous, 1980-probably 1981 (Box 8)
    1 compact sound cassette; contents could extend beyond 1980 into 1981?
  - Posłowie u Warskiego, 1981 March 28 (Box 8)
  - Kacprzak, Z., 1981 December 12-15 (Box 8)
  - Strajk w Stoczn. Warskiego, 1981 December 14 (Box 8)
  - Solidarność, Grudzień, Proces MKS Szczecin, 1981 December 29 - 1982 March 4 (Box 8)
  - Wyrok Bydgoszcz, 1982 March 4 (Box 8)
  - RWE / wyp. Kaczmarka w audycji A. Grabowska, 1982? (Box 8)
  - Polakiem być, 1982 October 11 (Box 8)
  - Helsingborg, 1987 November 8 (Box 8)
    3 compact sound cassettes
  - Jagielski, K., Radio "A", Helsingborg, 1987 November 12 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, before 1987 (Box 8)
  - Gdzie słońce wschodzi - Wincenty, 1981 January 15 (Record-cabinet cabinet)
    1 12-inch LP sound disc with original covers. Side A: Wypowiedzi Ojca św. Jana Pawła II i Lecha Wałesy podczas spotkania z przedstawicielami NSZZ "Solidarność" w Watykanie. Side B: Kompozycja Wincentego do tekstu poetyckego Czesława Miłosza p.t. "Pieśń niedobrych synów."
  - Pietrzyk, Maciej. Sierpień 80. [Warszawa]: Wifon, 1989 (Record-cabinet cabinet)
    1 12-inch LP sound disc with original covers.
- Oversize Material, 1980-1990
  - Solidarność, 1980 (Map-case case)
    1 nylon banner (91 x 147 cm), red and white with blank ink pen, hand-made.
  - Solidarność, circa 1980-1981 (Box 9)
    3 red ink on white nylon cloth strips (6 x 41 cm) intended as an arm band?
  - PLO [Polskie Linie Oceaniczne], 1980 (Box 9)
    1 blue ink on white nylon cloth armband.
  - Lech Walęsa, Czesław Miłosz, Jan Paweł II / [?]ardasinski, 1981 (Map-case case)
    Pen and ink drawing of the three men in 1 progression with John Paul II in profile (49 x 68 cm).
  - Wybory regionalne '81, Solidarność: ty deczydujesz, 1981 (Map-case case)
    2 posters (67 x 48 cm)
  - I krajowy zjazd delegatów NSZZ "Solidarność" Gdańsk, 1981 (Map-case case)
    1 poster (93 x 67 cm) of child walking in a field wearing a Solidarność shirt.
  - NSZZ rolników jndywidualnych Solidarność, 1981 (Box 9)
    1 cloth wall calendar (58 x 28 cm)
  - Wybierz najlepszych. Wybory do władz regionu Pomorza Zachodneigo, 1981 (Box 9)
    1 poster (42 x 30 cm)
  - Sam rząd to nie wszystko! Samorząd, before 1982 (Map-case case)
    1 poster (100 x 70 cm) with names "Socha" and Jędrczak in lower part of right margin.
  - Wolność dla wieżniów politycznych! Leszka Moczulskiego, Wojciecha Ziembińskiego, Tadeusza Stańskiego, Zygmunta Goławskiego, Jerzego Sychuta, Tadeusza Jańoziszaka, Krzysztofa Bzoyla / Komitet ObronyWięzionych za Przekonania, circa 1980-1982 (Box 9)
  - Wolność równość prawda, before 1982 (Box 9)
  - Być działaczem regionu Pomorza Zach. NSZZ Solidarność to znaczy być: odważnym, rozważnym, uczciwym, skromnym, kolezeńskim. Pomyśl o tym, zanim przyjmiesz funkcję, before 1982 (Box 9)
  - Pamiętaj wybory do władz regionalnych Pomorza Zachodniego muszą, nasz N.S.Z.Z. Solidarność, umocnić a nie osłabić!, before 1982 (Box 9)
  - Solidarność, 1983 (Box 9)
    3 cloth wall calendars (42 x 22 cm)
  - Polska Stefana Wyszyńskiego, Karola Wojtyły, Lecha Wałesy to Solidarność demokracja niepodległość / Stronnictwo Wiernośći Rzeczypospolitej - KSN, after 1988 (Box 9)
  - Głosuj na Solidarność, after 1988 (Box 9)
    1 poster (50 x 35 cm) of a girl holding a samorządni gospodarni...1990 placard.
  - 31 Sierpnia, 1980-1989, after 1988 (Box 9)
  - Polska potrzebuje Wałęsy / Zjednoczenie chrześcijańsko-narodowe, after 1988 (Box 9)
    1 poster (50 x 33 cm)
  - Obywatelu: nie pieprz bez sensu / Mleczko, after 1988 (Box 9)
    1 poster (42 x 30 cm) of a rhinoceros copulating with a giraffe.
  - Nasza parafia: biuletyn do użytku wewnętrznego, circa 1980-1990 (Box 9)
    1 broadside